Guide to the John Franklin Heitman Papers, 1863 - 1911 UA.29.02.0056
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Franklin Heitman papers
1863 - 1911
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Heitman, J. F. (John F.)
UA.29.02.0056
2.6 Linear Feet
John Franklin Heitman (1840-1904) was professor of Trinity College in Randolph County from 1883 to 1892, and Acting President of the school from 1884-1887. He later served as Headmaster of Trinity High School from 1892 to 1895. He also published several periodicals during his career. The John Franklin Heitman Papers contain correspondence, bound volumes, printed material, and financial and legal documents. Topics include college finance, the U.S. Government's sponsorship of education for Cherokee Indians, the Civil War, publications such as the North Carolina Education Journal and the North Carolina Home Journal, Trinity College administrative issues, and Trinity High School administrative issues. Major correspondents include Julian S. Carr and John W. Alspaugh. English.
1500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The John Franklin Heitman Papers were received as a transfer and gift in 1967.
Biographical Note
John Franklin Heitman was born on April 17, 1840 in Davidson County, North Carolina, the son of Henry and Eve McRary Heitman. He entered Trinity College in Randolph County in 1861, but left in 1862 to join the Confederate Army. He served as a captain in the Civil War. After the war, following a short period of business and teaching, he retuned to Trinity and received an A.M. degree in 1868. He then resumed teaching and became a clergyman in the Methodist Episcopal Church, South, and held several parishes. In 1881, he left the clergy to enter business in Chapel Hill, establishing the North Carolina Educational Journal, which he called "the organ of the North Carolina State Teachers Association."
During this time period, he met and married Emma Carr, sister of the Durham tobacco manufacturer Julian S. Carr. In 1883, he was appointed a professor at Trinity College and moved, along with the Education Journal, back to Randolph County. Much of his time over then next few years was spent in dealing with the financial problems of the school. After Marquis Lafayette Wood resigned from the presidency of Trinty in December 1884, Heitman served as an interim head of the school in his capacity as chairman of the faculty. Along with the Committee of Management--his brother-in-law Carr, J.W. Alspaugh, and James A. Gray--Heitman managed to keep the school financially afloat and increase enrollment. In 1887, a new president, John Franklin Crowell, was chosen to lead Trinity.
In 1892, Trinity College moved to Durham County, but Heitman stayed in Randolph County to become Headmaster of Trinity High School. In 1895 he was replaced as headmaster by the Board of Trustees of Trinity College. He then devoted his time to the North Carolina Home Journal, and continuing a series of articles on North Carolina history that he had begun in the North Carolina Educational Journal.
Heitman died on June 15, 1904, and is buried in Trinity Cemetery, Trinity, North Carolina, along with his wife. They had three children: Eva (Mrs. W. Bivens), Polly (Mrs. R.B. Terry), and John.
Collection Overview
The John Franklin Heitman Papers contain correspondence, bound volumes, printed material, and financial and legal documents. Much of the material dates from the 1884-1887 period in which Heitman served as Acting President of Trinity College. Topics include college finance, the U.S. Government's sponsorship of education for Cherokee Indians, the Civil War, publications, Trinity College administrative issues, and Trinity High School administrative issues. Major correspondents include Julian S. Carr and John W. Alspaugh.
This collection is arranged into two series. The first, Correspondence, dates from 1863 to 1894, with one letter from 1911. It includes both personal and professional correspondence, and is arranged chronologically. The second series, Bound Volumes and Other Material, includes a Civil War diary, grade books from Trinity High School, financial and legal documents related to Trinity College, and publications edited by Heitman, as well as a sampling of other types of print materials. This series is arranged alphabetically by topic.
Related Material
Kilgo (John C.) Records and Papers, 1888-1970 (bulk 1894-1920)
Duke University Archives
Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) Collection, 1836-1990
Duke University Archives
Cherokee Indians -- Education; Indians of North America -- Education (Higher) -- North Carolina; Diaries; The North Carolina educational journal [serial]; The N.C. home journal [serial]; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Carr, Julian Shakespeare; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.); Trinity High School (N.C.); Alspaugh, John W., 1831-1912; Heitman, J. F. (John F.); Heitman, J. F. (John F.); Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- Administration; Trinity College (Randolph County, N.C.) -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1863-1911
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of the correspondence dates from 1883 to 1887, when Heitman was Acting President of Trinity College, Randolph County. Issues include fund-raising and support of the college. Major correspondents include Julian S. Carr and J. W. Alspaugh, members of the committee of management that helped Heitman run the college from 1884 to 1887. As Trinity was one of the schools that contracted with the U.S. Government to educate Cherokee Indian youths, this series also contains correspondence between Heitman and the Bureau of Indian Affairs and the Department of the Treasury. Other correspondence is from applicants for positions and applicants for admissions to Trinity, correspondence regarding room and board, and letters from parents and prospective students.
  Other correspondence includes letters written during Heitman's Civil War days; correspondence concerning advertising, printing, and publicizing the North Carolina Educational Journal, as well as correspondence from subscribers, authors, and publishers; correspondence regarding Trinity High School, and a few family letters. Heitman's correspondence ends in 1894, but the collection contains one letter from 1911, from Heitman's wife to one of his daughters.
  The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - 1863-1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1874, 1880-September 1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - October 1883-December 1883 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - January 1884 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - February 1884 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - March 1884 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - April 1884 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - May 1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - June 1884-July 1884 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - August 1884-September 1884 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - October 1884-December 1884 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - January 1885-February 1885 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - March 1885-April 1885 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - May 1885 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - June 1885 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - July 1885 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - August 1885 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - September 1885 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - October 1885 (Box 2, Folder 18A)
  - November 1885-December 1885, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - January 1886 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - February 1886 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - March 1886 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - April 1886 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - May 1886 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - June 1886 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - July 1886 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - August 1886 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - September 1886 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - October 1886 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - November 1886-December 1886, no date (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - January 1887-March 1887 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - April 1887-May 1887 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - June 1887 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - July 1887-1888 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1889-1892 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 1893 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1894 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Bound Volumes and Other Material, 1863-1898
  The Bound Volumes and Other Material series contains items related to the Civil War, Trinity College (Randolph County), Trinity High School (Randolph County), and Heitman's publishing career. The Civil War diary concerns the Seige of Petersburg, retreat to Appomattox, and his imprisonment on Johnson's Island. A transcription is available. Other materials include financial and legal documents, printed material, and grade record books. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Bills, 1880-1894, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - The Carolina Wesleyan, Volume 1, No. 1, January 1, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Contains an autobiography by Heitman.
  - Civil War
    - Diary, 1864-1865 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Transcript of Diary, 1864-1865 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - North Carolina Home Journal, Volume 1, Nos. 1 and 9, 1897-1898 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Printed Material, circa 1880-1894 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Includes ads, tickets, notices, and other materials used by Heitman in his publishing and administrative career.
  - Printed Material, circa 1884-1894 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Contains commencement programs and other announcements from Southern high schools and colleges.
  - Trinity College, Randolph County
    - Account Book, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Financial Records, Claims, 1882-1886, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Legal Papers, 1882-1886 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Trinity High School, Randolph County
    - Class Record Book, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Class Record Book, possibly for Trinity High School, circa 1898 (Box 3, Folder 50)